[SPEAKER_00]: So, we can go through ānāpānasati sutta now, which is a Majjhima hundred and eighteen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness of breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says that, on one occasion, the Buddha was living at Savatthi, in the Eastern Park, in Migara's mother's place, with many well-known elder disciples, Venerable Sariputta, Maha Mughalana, Maha Kasuppa, Maha Kacchayana, Maha Kotika, Maha Kapina, Maha Chunda, Venerable Anuruddha, Venerable Ananda, together with other well-known elder disciples.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, those disciples, those elders bhikkhus, were exhorting, instructing junior bhikkhus, eh... sometimes ten, twenty, thirty, forty bhikkhus at a time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And those junior bhikkhus, being exhorted, being instructed, sooner or later understood the Noble Attainments.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the Buddha said that, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Upon the completion of pavārana, on the full moon of the 15th poster day, the Buddha was sitting down in the open, surrounded by the bhikkhu saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the Buddha, having surveyed the completely silent saṅgha of bhikkhus, addressed the bhikkhus, I'm resolved upon this path of practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: My mind is resolved upon this path of practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, bhikkhus, make even more of an effort to reach the unreached, to attain the unattained, to realize the unrealized.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the bhikkhus from the countryside returned to Savatthi to see the Buddha, and then the other bhikkhus continued to exhort junior bhikkhus 10, 20, 30, 40 at a time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... on the next full moon, eh... on the full moon night of Komudi, the fourth month, the Buddha was sitting down in the open, surrounded by bhikkhu saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having completely surveyed the silent saṅgha bhikkhus, he addressed the bhikkhus.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, bhikkhus, disassembly is free from chit-chat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, disassembly is free from the idle chatter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Purity has been established in its essence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Such is this saṅgha of bhikkhus.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that, eh... that clearly indicates that the saṅgha of the bhikkhus that the Buddha was praising was, eh... basically an ārya saṅgha, which means there were no putujanas there.
[SPEAKER_00]: There were no...
[SPEAKER_00]: In this saṅgha of bhikkhus, there are arahants, with thanes destroyed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having come to an end, done what should be done, laid down the burden, reached the cause of peace, with the fetters of existence wasted away, liberated by right understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Such is this saṅgha of bhikkhus.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this saṅgha of bhikkhus, there are bhikkhus with five lower fetters wasted away,
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, in this saṅgha of bhikkhus, there are bhikkhus with the three fetters wasted away, with greed, hatred and delusion reduced, once returners, who, having come to this world once, will make an end to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Such is this saṅgha of bhikkhus.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, in this saṅgha of bhikkhus, there are bhikkhus with the three fetters wasted away, stream-enterers,
[SPEAKER_00]: of the nature of the lower realms certain of having an end in full awakening because there's such because in this saṅgha because so um so yes the uh the entire bhikkhu saṅgha there that the buddha um instructed beforehand that he said make the effort and reach the unreached attain the unattained realize the unrealized
[SPEAKER_00]: There was an Arya Saṅgha, and it's important to note, well, we'll see why, but it's... there were no there were no putujanas in that assembly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for those who were not yet arahants, who still had work to do, then the Buddha decided, in this particular sutta, to to instruct on mindfulness of breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before he started, he listed all the ways that these bhikkhus, who are not shortened and sotāpannas, can do the rest of the work that they need to do and reach the unreached and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, the bhikkhus... there are bhikkhus who dwell practicing the practice of the development of the four ways to set up mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are such bhikkhus in the Saṅgha of Bhikkhus.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the Noble... in the Noble Arya Saṅgha, there are bhikkhus who practice satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then bhikkhus, in this saṅgha of bhikkhus, the noble saṅgha of bhikkhus, there are bhikkhus who dwell practicing the practice of development of the Four Right Efforts, the Four Foundations of Potency, the Five Strengths, the bhikkhus who practice Seven Factors of Awakening, the bhikkhus who practice the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are such bhikkhus in this saṅgha of bhikkhus.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this saṅgha of bhikkhus, there are bhikkhus who dwell practicing the practice of development of loving-kindness, development of compassion, development of gladness,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all these relatively popular, or certainly familiar practices in contemporary Buddhism, are practiced by those who are not shorted in sotāpannas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is something that Venerable Ñānavira was saying, but I said and I repeat it often.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need the right view in order to know what to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, in order to know how to practice, you need to understand what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the most obvious reasoning.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can arrive there by reasoning, that you can't do something unless you know what you're supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the Buddha insists on enlisting all these people who are there, then none of them, that's like pure heartwood, and none of them is shorter than like a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, these are the practices that these noble disciples would do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, that doesn't mean that the person shouldn't keep trying to understand what these practices are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because through understanding, you will become at least a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem is that in certainly in the contemporary Buddhism, the one that you hear a lot in the West,
[SPEAKER_00]: People believe that automatically doing these things as some sort of technique or some sort of repetitive method, you will arrive at understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they can be done properly only by those who already understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's sort of self-defeating, if it's done improperly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Which page are we on now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's get on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it says, because in this saṅgha, because there are bhikkhus who dwell practicing practice of the development of mindfulness of breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness of breathing, when developed, made much of, is of great fruit, great benefit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness of breathing, when developed, made much of, fulfills the four ways to set up mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Another contemporary, well-established perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it comes to ānāpānasati, is that, eh... you do ānāpānasati in the form of watching your nostrils, or similar, and you enter the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Automatically, you will eventually enter the jhāna, have the experience of jhāna through watching your nostrils.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah... and here it is, THE sutta in question, the ānāpānasati sutta, and there's absolutely no mention of that whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says that by developing the mindfulness of breathing, you develop
[SPEAKER_00]: Surprise!
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You develop the four foundations of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: By developing the four foundations of mindfulness, you automatically get a jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You develop the seven factors of awakening.
[SPEAKER_00]: By developing seven factors of awakening, you develop wisdom and liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: You become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: In some other talks, that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mentioned the relationship between ānāpānasati and jhāna, as in ānāpānasati, or many other ways of developing mindfulness, can serve as a basis for you to attend to the theme of jhāna, as the Buddha would describe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, on account of that, develop mindfulness on the basis of breathing or something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Properly develop mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can develop theme of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But thinking that doing a meditation method of watching your breath automatically results in jhāna, that all came much later, and it's certainly not found in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, the Buddha carries on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Developed in what way?
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhu is made much of in what ways?
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness of breathing of much fruit, much benefit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhu has gone to the forest, gone to the root of a tree, gone to an empty dwelling, sits down, having crossed leg... crossed his legs, making his back straight, having set up mindfulness in front.
[SPEAKER_00]: We spoke about it in the first audio talk about mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just mindful he breathes in, just mindful he breathes out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Breathing in long, he understands I'm breathing in long.
[SPEAKER_00]: Breathing out long, he understands I'm breathing out long.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not focusing on what he's doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not trying to attend and catch every moment and see things arising and passing away.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands what he's doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands what's occurring.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in order for something...
[SPEAKER_00]: In order for you to understand something, you cannot be absorbed in it, forcefully absorbed, even worse, prying upon like a... like a... like a... like a... like an owl trying to catch a fish.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to understand what's going on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means you already need to start paying attention to the nature of what's present, the nature of your action, in this case, the nature of breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he understands what he's doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's breathing in lung, he understands he's breathing in lung, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Experiencing the whole body, he trains.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will breathe in as one who experiences the whole body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, we mentioned that in the previous talk.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that body, that peripheral mindfulness, the image of the body that appears, that's discerned in that indirect manner within the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I'll have to stop saying peripheral mindfulness, because it's just mindfulness, but... Well, I want to stop saying, but I can't, because obviously, if I say mindfulness,
[SPEAKER_00]: People will regard that as coming under any idea of mindfulness that they might have.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the body, the imaginal body that appears in the peripheral mindfulness, the properly established mindfulness, eh... that's the body that you're trying to experience, without attending it, without making it a foreground, without making it an object.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in the same manner, that's how you start calming the determinations of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: The determinations of that... those peripheral images.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same manner, I will breathe in as one who experiences joy, experiences pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all done on that background level.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, the more you discern the background, you realize how much input you can have in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without overattending it, without trying to make it an object of your meditation, but discerning it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, it carries on.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will breathe in as one who experiences the determinations of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will breathe out as one who experiences the determinations of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Determinations of the mind being perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you cannot possibly attend perception and feeling at the same time as a meditation object.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can certainly discern them in the periphery.
[SPEAKER_00]: Usually, it's the feeling that is discerned on the peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the craving is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where everything else is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I will breathe in as one who experiences that mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will breathe out as the one who experiences that mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: He will enjoy the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: He will compose the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: He will liberate the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind being the ultimate negative, the ultimate background, the ultimate general, the ultimate peripheral, determined by that which appears in front of your perception, by the feeling,
[SPEAKER_00]: That experience of those two things, that are simultaneously present in itself, that experience is the mind, and you cannot possibly attend to that, because that would require you to step outside of that mind, and then look at it as an object.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can certainly discern its outlines, and then discern its signs, the citta, nimitta, and that is all in that peripheral that we talk about very often.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, developed in this way, because made much of it in this way, mindfulness of breathing is of great fruit, great benefit.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it says, so, in what way bhikkhu is made mature?
[SPEAKER_00]: In what way does mindfulness of breathing fulfill the four ways to set up mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_00]: The four satipaṭṭhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, on whatever occasion, a bhikkhu breathing in long, understands and breathing in long, or breathing out long, understands and breathing out long, or breathing in short, understands and breathing in short, or breathing out short, understands and breathing out short.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu dwells as an observer of body in the body, ardent, aware, mindful, having removed covetousness and unhappiness in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this way, I speak of certain body within the bodies that is in and out breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the body that you start discerning peripherally, on account of your mindfulness of in and out breathing, is that which stands for your experience of the body there.
[SPEAKER_00]: We said that before, but it certainly doesn't hurt repeating it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, it goes further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, on whatever occasion, bhikkhu trains, I will breathe in as the one who experiences joy, breathing as the one... breathing out as the one who experiences joy, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says that then, on that occasion, the bhikkhu dwells
[SPEAKER_00]: As an observer of feeling in feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a simultaneous presence of feeling within a feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ardent, aware, mindful, having removed covetousness and unhappiness in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, by the way, when we talk about simultaneous presence, it doesn't mean there are two things simultaneously arisen for a second, or two, or a moment, and you must catch them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means that they endure on two different levels of generality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a mood, for example, you can be in the same mood for two or three days, while on a more particular level, you can have various sort of fleeting perceptions or feelings of a lower kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And those two domains remain simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you become... if your mindfulness gets established upon the general mood,
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't be affected and you will certainly be mindful automatically of all the things that arise within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what it meant he's mindful of body within the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're mindful or feeling within the feeling or feeling in the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when a person is mindful of the peripheral image of the body that they have, the body there out in the world,
[SPEAKER_00]: Any particular attention given to the body that appears as an object for you, that's within that body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't have to be chasing it or trying to not lose it, because that's automatically in the body that you are already mindful of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a gatekeeper.
[SPEAKER_00]: You find a gate, and then you don't have to chase the things that go in.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just stay at the gate, mindful, knowingly, that if you stay at the gate, you know exactly who is inside and who goes outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was a simile from the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean you stare at the gate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a robot.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every second, try to not blink.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you blink at the gate... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just stand there, and you will know who passes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how a monk is properly mindful of feelings in the feelings, or feeling within the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You find the general feeling, which will then automatically include whatever is particularly felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not focusing hard on a particular feeling, and then try to discern feeling within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So bhikkhus, on whatever occasion bhikkhu trains, I will experience as the one who experiences the mind, I will breathe out as the one who experiences the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu dwells as an observer of mind within the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ardent, aware, mindful, having removed covetousness and unhappiness in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, for the one who is forgetful, unaware, I do not speak of mindfulness of breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: On whatever occasion bhikkhu trains, I will breathe in as the one who sees impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will breathe out as the one who sees impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will breathe in as the one who sees dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will breathe out as the one who sees dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will breathe in as the one who sees cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will breathe out as the one who sees cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's basically when you discern the phenomenon of the peripheral, the dhamma of the peripheral, the nature of the peripheral, the nature of mindfulness, you automatically see that anything you attend within that experience is within that peripheral.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those dhammas are already within these general dhammas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having understood the general nature of a phenomenon, you have understood any single individual manifestation of that nature, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: a particular phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, developed in this way, because made much in this way, mindfulness of breathing fulfills the four ways to set up mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it says, eh... because in what way, made much of in what way, does the four ways of setting up mindfulness fulfill the seven factors of awakening?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because on whatever occasion a bhikkhu dwells as an observer of body-in-body, ardent, aware, mindful, having removed covetousness and unhappiness in the world, on that occasion, having set up mindfulness, he is not forgetful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because on whatever occasion a bhikkhu's mindfulness is set up, he is not forgetful, on that occasion, a bhikkhu's mindfulness factor of awakening is aroused.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu develops the mindfulness factor of awakening.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu's mindfulness factor of awakening goes to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again,
[SPEAKER_00]: If a person sort of has trouble understanding what we mean by mindfulness, peripheral mindfulness, dwell on the phenomenon of forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remember things when you have a composure present in your mind, when it's like a general presence of your mind, not when you sort of are focusing on sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, sensations in your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: That does not maintain your non-forgetfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That actually takes you the way of
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't want to find one point, like one-pointedness, often translated.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can call it one-pointedness, but there's a way of becoming one-pointed by focusing so hard on an object of your perception, even sensations, bodily sensations, which is just object of perception of touch, whereby you forget everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And sensuality works exactly the same way.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the mind gets bent on having something, you pretty much lose perspective on everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, there is the one-pointedness that we talk about, which is you find a more general point, like the domain of the peripheral, for example, the background of your experience, that then automatically includes everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not the one-pointedness that makes you absorbed, so you forget everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the one-pointedness that there's nothing left out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is included.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, then he goes further.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how to develop mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, dwelling mindful in this way, he thinks about, he ponders over, he undergoes an investigation of a phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, that is pretty self-explanatory.
[SPEAKER_00]: You actually actively make the effort to think and understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the only way the understanding can come about, and with mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he may... he undergoes an investigation of that phenomenon with an understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, on whatever occasion, bhikkhu dwelling mindful in this way, thinks about, ponders over, undergoes an investigation of the phenomena with an understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu... bhikkhu's investigation of phenomena, factor of awakening, is aroused.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dhamma vijaya.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu develops the investigation of phenomena, factor of awakening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, for one, thinking about, pondering over, undergoing an investigation of the phenomena, understanding, active energy is aroused.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu's thinking about, pondering over, undergoing an investigation of that phenomena, with an understanding, active energy is aroused.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu's energy factor of awakening is aroused.
[SPEAKER_00]: That energy factor of awakening goes to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: For the one with energy aroused, a joy not of the flesh arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means a joy not of a bodily kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what joy is not of a bodily kind?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the joy of knowledge, joy of discernment, joy of peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's in the background of that which is your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is no other body where it could be.
[SPEAKER_00]: No other space for it to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's either in the body or it's in your mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, on whatever occasion that joy arises, the body calms down, and then the mind calms down.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu's tranquility factor of awakening is aroused.
[SPEAKER_00]: With a tranquil body, for one who is happy, the mind is composed.
[SPEAKER_00]: On whatever occasion, for a bhikkhu with a tranquil body, for one who is happy, the mind is composed.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu's composure factor of awakening is aroused.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu develops the composure factor of awakening, and that composure factor goes to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: He is the one who looks on properly at the mind composed in this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: On whatever occasion, a bhikkhu is the one who looks on properly at the mind composed in this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu's indifference factor of awakening is aroused.
[SPEAKER_00]: Upeka.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the bhikkhu develops the indifference factor of awakening.
[SPEAKER_00]: On that occasion, the indifference factor goes to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: bhikkhus, on whatever occasion, bhikkhu dwells as an observer of feeling and feeling, mind and mind, phenomena and phenomena, ardent, aware, mindful, having removed covetousness and unhappiness in the world, in regard to the world, on that occasion, having set up mindfulness, he is not forgetful.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he goes to repeat dhamma, vijaya, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, in what way, because
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, the seven factors of enlightenment... of awakening fulfill wisdom and liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, Bhikkhu Zubikkhu develops the mindfulness factor of awakening, supported by seclusion, supported by dispassion, supported by cessation, resulting in relinquishment.
[SPEAKER_00]: He develops the investigational phenomena factor of the awakening, the energy factor of awakening, the joy factor of awakening, develops the tranquility factor of awakening, develops the composure factor of awakening.
[SPEAKER_00]: He develops the indifference factor of awakening, supported by seclusion, supported by dispassion, supported by cessation, resulting in relinquishment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Developed in this way, the same factors awakening fulfill the wisdom and liberation, full understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: One becomes an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that concludes this Ānāpānasati Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, this audio can go in conjunction with the mindfulness of the body, certainly the part one of that, of those audio notes, because it's... lots of things that I mentioned, they are fully applicable here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most notably, obviously, that one needs to have the right view in order to do this practice correctly, and to stop expecting an automatic result of some sort of experience, confused to be jhāna, coming out of watching the nostrils, or watching the belly, or whichever way people do mindfulness of breathing today.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness of breathing is about understanding the nature of action of breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could say it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's understanding, like, I'm breathing in long, I understand I'm breathing in long.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to keep telling to myself that I'm breathing in lung.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to keep attending every, every second of that breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, of that breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I understand what I'm doing, while I'm doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the essence of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing what you're doing, while you're doing it, means being peripherally aware of what's directly happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that should be enough for now.